Let's just discuss maybe
just Sati. Sati.
Yeah.
What is Sati? What is it?
Yeah, what is Sati?
mindfulness. What is Sati and why it's
better to not translate it as
mindfulness? Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
As you saying, it's better to translate
it
well, it's the option Mhm. as recollection.
it's the option Mhm. as recollection.
Yes, Sati. Recollectedness, I suppose.
Recollectedness. Cuz it's about
remembering something.
Yeah. A specific thing.
A specific thing.
Yeah.
Remembering is not doing.
Mhm. Mhm. So, what is the Well, What is
the nature then?
So, given that Sati
even in the Suttas it's it's used as
memory. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Um one who
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Um one who
remembers things.
One who remembers things. Um yeah.
So, what is the nature of
recollecting?
What is a necessary condition for you to
recollect something?
Remember when experience that's
What is a necessary condition? Yeah, so
in order for you to recollect something
knowledge. So, you need to know what you're
So, you need to know what you're
recollecting. Can you recollect
something you never ever
experienced or or came across
or thought of? Can you recollect such
things? No.
No.
Exactly. So, it's
The necessary condition for Sati is at
least a degree of some discernment of
something. Cuz there is nothing to be recollected.
Cuz there is nothing to be recollected.
How can recollection take place?
Impossible. So, the effort of Sati is the effort of
So, the effort of Sati is the effort of
um recollecting.
Either what you discerned
or recollecting that which you basically
learn that the same
recollecting what you learned that
discernment is.
So, in other words, even if somebody who
doesn't necessarily have the the values
of a Sotapanna or or or somebody in
training to recollect them.
The nature of Sati is the nature of
recollecting. So, you recollect the
purpose of your practice. You recollect
that you are responsible for your
actions. Things that puthujjana can
know. That's what your mindfulness is.
Not like I recollect it and now I forget
about it.
If I ask you, can you
um bring back to your mind basically,
recollect uh
all the times or rather recollect how
you felt all the times that you suffered
in your life on account of anything.
Doesn't matter what specifically. Just
recollect the nature of suffering. Mhm.
And now go about your day
with that recollection in your mind.
And that's nothing other than telling
you how to go about your day being
mindful of your feelings.
And does that recollection have to be
in front of you? Not just that it
doesn't have to be, it cannot be in
front of you. Cuz you're recollecting
something that's not there. Even if like
would you be recollecting now that you
are uh I don't know clasping your hands
uh I don't know clasping your hands
together. Oh, I'm recollecting this.
No, recollection is always on the level
of the context of now. Yes. So, if
you're doing your recollection now,
means you're not seeing the context.
The context being the the more the the
general nature of things that you're
supposed to discern. So, in this
particular instance
uh context being your body posture and
having hands and having life and not
being dead and all these other things.
All these other things you can use to be
mindful of.
So, being mindful of something doesn't
mean attending and focusing on that
thing. Means discerning the peripheral
context in regard to that thing.
Remembering the context.
Remembering. You don't say remembering the context
You don't say remembering the context
cuz that imply you can remember
something else. No, you can't. That's
all you can remember.
That's all you can recollect is
something that is to a degree known as
an experienced discerned. Maybe not
fully understood.
But again, you know you're responsible
for your actions. It's when you forget
that. Basically think that you always are
Basically think that you always are
responsible for your actions, that's
when you start acting irresponsibly.
Would you be acting irresponsibly with
the thought in your mind resulting from
directly like recollecting the weight of
responsibility that you know you have?
You wouldn't. You couldn't.
Or would you be acting sensually towards
sense desire having established your
mind properly recollected the sign of
repulsiveness, the inherent
repulsiveness in everything beautiful,
the inherent impermanence, the inherent
danger? Those are the thoughts you recollect.
Those are the thoughts you recollect.
But those thoughts are the context of
your present situation.
So, for as long as you think you can
keep you can be doing mindfulness in the
present moment, means you are not
mindful because you are doing it.
You're not recollecting it, you're
trying to basically perform it.
And mindfulness and discernment is not
on the level of performing. That's why
it cannot be a method, it cannot be a
technique, it cannot be a doing. And
that's why it can free you from doing.
If there is a prescribed set of oh, you
do this, you do this, you do this and
you're free from doing. That's a
contradiction in terms.
Yeah, do good on account of doing bad.
So, stop doing bad but do good but it's
still a form of doing. You're still
bound by by nature of action.
But discerning the context, discerning
the nature of it, that's where the
freedom is. That's why you can't have
too much of Sati.
And that's why Sati results in in
discernment, in full understanding of
nature of things.
And that's why also Sati,
recollectedness uh results in Samadhi.
uh results in Samadhi.
Which is composure.
You are composed right here right now as
a result of my fundamental impeachable
recollected context that is still
enduring unchanged.
That's like all the things you can be
mindful of. Your moods, the context,
your feelings, the context of your
actions. What death? Death, the context, yeah.
What death? Death, the context, yeah.
Uh So, it's not being mindful of any old
thing. It's like
you need to discern what it is.
Of yeah, if
if you're actually practicing
recollectedness for the sake of freedom
from suffering, you need to know what
you're supposed to recollect.
What you're supposed to
uh
bring back into your mind to to endure
as a context.
And essentially a puthujjana won't see
He cannot know that because he doesn't
he doesn't he doesn't see the Dhamma.
So, he doesn't know what
the way out of suffering. How can he
recollect the way out of suffering?
Having not found the way out of
suffering, he cannot recollect it.
That's why the mundane right view for
puthujjana is something he needs to
strive for. That there is
responsibility, there is result of your
actions, there is given, there are
things that I don't understand and so on
and so forth. Basically taking it into
account that you don't know and you
acknowledge that.
And that's again, you recollect that
context. So, see if you if your mind is
established upon the context of um
oh, I don't know. I don't know the way
out of suffering.
And that remains. You you don't neglect
neglect that recollection.
When it sort of lapses, you bring back
that recollection.
You you re-clarify it. You re-discern
it, so to speak. Would you then be able
to to to take, leave, pick or choose or
dismiss various instructions of the
Suttas you come across? You wouldn't.
Because you know that you don't know,
which means you know that you don't have
a reference point for right as right,
wrong as wrong. So, you would take
everything with a pinch of salt but at
the same time you wouldn't look for
fault into things either.
So, you would be careful and maintain
the context of the one who doesn't know,
who's trying to figure it out.
Or also, if you are maintaining the
context of the one who doesn't know,
would you then be able to um
forget about the fact that you don't
know and that you're subjected to
suffering and and the whole No, you
wouldn't. It would be it would become a
pressing task for you to do.
But when you don't necessarily dwell on
the context that you don't know
you sort of drift like you know if
somebody were to like ask you, put you
on the spot, you'll say yes, I don't
know. But if nobody asks you, if you
don't ask yourself that question, if you
don't bring that recollection to your
mind, you will drift away on account of
things that you do that make you feel
better, that make you be a nicer person
and so on. And you land up being a
puthujjana who thinks he knows what
practice of Dhamma is. And that's like
the the greatest obstruction you create
for yourself cuz then you won't look for
what the right Dhamma is.
And the right Dhamma begins when when
you know the way out of suffering.
Not before that.
Yeah, maybe you're doing it rightly.
Maybe you're doing it rightly. The
context is I still don't know, which
means I mustn't stop trying to find it
find the right thing
uh until I know for sure. And that will
come as a That kind of uh sense of
urgency would come as a direct direct
result of your correct or
recollectedness of the correct things.
But even as I said, even if you don't
necessarily have any Dhamma instruction
um Sati,
mindfulness is recollectedness. Mhm.
Like as as as they don't look at the
example like that. Oh, be be mindful
when you're going to the cootie because
there is a slippery gutter there.
So now you go into the cootie and you're
opening the door carefully and you're
carefully putting your foot down so you
don't slip and then the second step
carefully. That's not what mindfulness
is. That's not what sati is.
All of those things you're doing
carefully are results of your sati which
is awareness of the context of danger.
So that's the context of entering the
cootie's potential injury.
Because of that you are stepping in
slowly. But most people probably due to the
But most people probably due to the
whole kind of notion of you know
meditative techniques and whatnot
associate mindfulness with that kind of
close attention like staring at my
feeling the soles of my foot. I'm
mindful. No. You wouldn't even do that
unless somebody pointed out the possible
danger of slipping.
And that's where the mindfulness is in
discerning the context of your present
intentions that are leading you towards
present actions. Not towards like
canceling everything. Like don't don't
think about the context. Don't think
about the fear. Don't think about the
danger. Just touching touching moving
moving opening sitting stepping whatever
else. That's like completely the
opposite of the context.
And ironically
that's also done on account of the
context context of ignoring.
You value ignoring the context as a
practice of dhamma.
So that's where we want to commit and
overly absorb into things. Hopefully
that that's how you kind of pull
yourself away from all the thoughts and
feelings and moods that are bothering
you. I mean how many times you heard
from you know the teachers oh just stop
thinking. Or just place your awareness
on the breath.
Which is again just just focus on
breathing or do the mantra Buddha in
your head. Just don't think.
How can you even understand that
sentence without thinking it?
So here you are thinking that you
shouldn't be thinking.
And then adhering to your thinking that
thinks that doesn't think as the way of
out of thinking.
And that's where it always results in
just frustration basically.
And if people think if people who are
engaging in this kind of practice you
know I'm not frustrated. Well,
then you could also ask yourself do you
get upset when somebody says that your
practice is wrong?
Do you get defensive?
Cuz if that sort of
um
starts you off
in a defensive direction means oh so
you're adhering to something blindly.
Why you why you why you being affected
by coming across a a view that says no
that's wrong?
You don't need to take it personally and
if you're doing it rightly you would be
unable to take it personally.
So all these little pointers basically
but they're not seen because the whole
practice is practice of looking away
from the context.
Ironically at the pretext of mindfulness
which is basically recollectiveness of
the context.
And you could see if the context is
clearly discerned
and it's enduring there presently now
you're responsible for your actions.
Mean you are you will be acting whatever
you now choose to do within that context
you will be acting in full awareness.
Because the contest context is clear and
impeccable. Can you then act in lack of awareness
Can you then act in lack of awareness
and do something irresponsible while the
context of responsibility is there
enduring and you're feeling it? You
can't. Impossible. Hence sati sampajanna
mindfulness recollectiveness and and awareness.
So you can't do mindfulness. That's the
point. If you're doing it means that's
not mindfulness.
Your doing is the result of
recollectiveness or lack of it.
That's why they you know the right view
comes first even for the right
mindfulness. Doesn't say sammasati comes
first and then sammaditthi comes first
second. No.
It's the right view that then ah now you
know what you're supposed to recollect and
what you're supposed to recollect and
now your recollectiveness will be
sammasati.
Or do a right technique that will then
result in the right view. Impossible.
So having developed right view having
discerned the right view
your recollectiveness will be right.
Having discerned the right view having
right recollectiveness enduring your
composure will be right.
Sammasamadhi.
So having recognized the context
Mhm. and having
and having
remem- and remembering the context.
Yeah. And Like no and see like
remembering the context people might
think ah so I I just have to keep
telling to myself what the context is.
That's not remembering the context.
That's you just basically trying to do
it again.
So remembering the context means
recollect are you responsible for your
actions? Or like what I would what we
always do. What is your present enduring
mood right now?
Positive negative neutral.
See you recollect what's already there.
You're not creating the mood by giving
me the answer. You just
the question directed you in the in the
in the direction of the context which is
the presently enduring pleasant mood.
Ah
okay. Now you don't have to keep saying I'm
Now you don't have to keep saying I'm
I'm in a good mood good mood good mood.
That will distract you from presently
enduring mood.
So now you just have to remain mindful
of it peripherally. That's the whole
point. That's what mindfulness is that
peripheral discernment.
Discernment of the container of the
foundation. would it would it be like if you said
would it would it be like if you said
remembering or or um
recollecting right recollecting it?
It's not so much as something that you
do but not not um
engaging in anything
that contradicts it. Ah
protecting what you recollected. Yeah.
That's what Buddha would say in that
sutta to the everybody mischants.
That you you you guard your mind. Mhm.
Like the mother guards her own child.
Mhm. And with that state of mind you will
And with that state of mind you will
cherish all living beings. Mhm.
But I mean this is like unrelated but
the funny thing is the way the chanting
is done and translated it sounds as if
um
you will basically like the mother
guards her own child you cherish all
living beings.
But the point is to recollect the mind
correctly protect the mind as in protect
the wholesome states.
Yeah. Because if
Because if
Make sure there is no arising of
unwholesome and no cessation of of
wholesome. And if you engage in
something if you choose to engage in
something unwholesome then you're
basically preventing yourself from
recollecting. so you are practicing mindfulness by
so you are practicing mindfulness by
knowing what you're supposed to
recollect which is already a form of
recollecting it.
And then protecting that which is
enduring through that recollection which
is your state of mind.
You're recollecting. Yeah you
recollected it. So what do I do now? Let
it endure without distracting yourself
from it. Mhm. So you and that's what we
spoke in the
previous talk. You can't lose your
recollectiveness accidentally. You only lose it when you
accidentally. You only lose it when you
choose to basically act out of
desire aversion or desire for
distraction. So through your actions you basically
So through your actions you basically
erode the context that you now do need
to re-recollect.
But you can still do it you
re-recollected then your actions
are seen as discrepant to the context
that now you value like a mother values
her only child.
And then you will abstain from the
actions and it will be it won't require
effort and and like oh I must say no I
must say no because you value the
context and these actions are
incompatible with the context. The only
reason you can then engage with these
actions is if you stop recollecting stop
or lose the what you recollected
of that context.
And you will lose it
when you carelessly take it for granted
start looking away from it start
distracting. Oh this is fine this won't
take me away from my recollectiveness da
da da da da da da.
Next thing you know you lost what you
recollected so you need to redo it.
But one who has recognized that what
needs to be recollected Mhm.
and Then you just maintain that
recollection in being which is the
definition of bhavana.
Maintaining it like like protect it
while it's enduring there on its own
because that's the context you you
discern. And as a result of you
protecting the context now that's that's
being there enduring as your state of
mind everything incompatible to that context
everything incompatible to that context
is being sort of you know burnt away.
So it's like you've understood something
and now you're not doing anything that's
going to
confuse that. There's going to come in
and distract you from it.
Mindfulness Mindfulness of breathing.
Recollect Yeah recollectiveness of
breathing. Recollectiveness of breathing.
Recollectiveness of breathing.
Well that's as we already clarified in a
number of talks on kind of peripheral
awareness um
um
we done the whole talk of mindfulness of
breath basically discernment of the
context that endured while you're doing
this while you're doing that and so on.
Well now in the light of the recent talk
of recollectiveness being the word for
sati Um
Um
you read the sutta
in itself Anapanasati sutta and it
already states that states first that
the audience of the Anapanasati sutta
were at least sort of panas
which means they were all of the right
view. So now they have the right
mindfulness. And then there are different loads of
And then there are different loads of
ways of right mindfulness but in this
particular sutta the way of the right
sorry recollection is is the
recollection of breathing.
And that's that's how the the actual
instruction starts.
Breathing in long as in there is
breathing in long he knows he's
breathing in long.
So it's not like I am breathing in long
and I know I'm breathing in long.
Breathing in long while breathing in
long he knows there is a breathing in
long. So you you recollect the most obvious
So you you recollect the most obvious
the most apparent the most neutral
knowledge of what's already there.
Can you recollect the breath?
If the breath is not there.
Impossible. And that's important order here to
And that's important order here to
maintain because
when people would even read that sutta
which is very clear but yeah I'm sure
people say well it's very clear that's
an instruction and then people take it
to be an instruction. But it doesn't he
say he knows. He doesn't say he does the
breath like this.
So while breathing like this he knows
that's what that's how he's breathing.
He knows he's breathing in long he
knows. So can you do the knowledge?
So can you do the knowledge?
Oh do the knowledge. Do the knowledge
for me.
Do the mad method of knowledge.
No you can only know what's there you
can only know that's why knowledge
results from correct recollection. You
get to know what you keep recollecting.
And the only reason by the way you can
then practice whatever focusing on your
nostrils or other breath is because of
the context of the breathing is there
that obviously now you're not mindful
of.
You lost the recollection of it. Cuz you
don't need to be thinking of your
nostrils in order to know that you are
breathing. All you need to do is don't distract
All you need to do is don't distract
yourself from that you your knowledge
that you are already breathing. So you
said um well you can see how you breathing
um well you can see how you breathing
now.
Doesn't matter you don't have to
you don't have to start your knowledge
by
the first
thing that you say.
This is how I supposed to be breathing
in something like that.
Okay so So now I've got the long breath
and now I've got the short breath at the
moment. so I have to wait for the long yeah
so I have to wait for the long yeah
yeah. And then No you got to do the long
breathing first and then you
So you start you start the mindfulness
of breathing by asking yourself am I
breathing right now?
The answer is yes.
So what is the breathing while I'm
breathing?
Well breathing is in breathing is out
breathing is bodily in of air bodily out
of air. That's the breathing and I know
I'm breathing because breathing is there
while I'm thinking of it.
That's the beginning of mindfulness of
breath. When you get used to that
context then yeah you can see oh now
there is this kind of breathing in and
this kind of breathing out that you know
not that you do.
It's like knowing the mind in this
respect. Yeah. The same
Yeah. The same
Yeah yeah yeah of course. Knowing the
context exactly. And and it's like
basically
there's something there that you
you're kind of um
You can say there is breathing that is
on its own. Exactly yeah there's when
you say and you know it.
That you either recollect it to be
there. Exactly. And that's what that's
what I meant. I don't actually know if I
finished the sentence. But yeah good
point. That's what I said it's important
order because if you
don't discern that or if you forget that
you you will keep trying to repossess
your breathing to re regain the control
of your breathing
which is completely the opposite of
recognizing it being there on its own
independent of you.
So you're taking away that which you
can't take away which is the
independence of the form of the body of
the feelings and trying to recontrol and
again that's why most people's
meditation is meditation with centrality
which is meditation with control with
desire with like this with like that.
You're recognizing what the breath is in
that context of it. Recognizing what
currently what breath currently is enduring on its
what breath currently is enduring on its
own.
Recognizing breath peripherally. It I
think it it takes the verb actually so I
I would tend to avoid saying
recollection of the breath because it's
something that you're doing it's
something that's it's an intention. It's
like um
so it's it's actually the verb breathing
in. So it's recollecting breathing in
So it's recollecting breathing in
rather than
the well just for me the breath when I
say recollection of the breath or
mindfulness of the breath people think
oh well it's this
Being present while I'm doing this.
thing that I focus on.
Yeah. Yeah.
Focus on this while I'm doing it.
Yeah yeah yeah.
No it's yeah that's what I mean like
breathing in breathing out is there.
They're bound with the body they're
bodily they're being done by the body.
So you are discerning
that. So breathing in long he knows breathing
So breathing in long he knows breathing
in is long.
Not like I am breathing in.
Later on
and that's that's what you got to phone
up. That's why I brought that sutta.
Want to look at the Pali as well. Yeah.
Yeah so the first
few are breathing in long
I am breathing in long.
So he knows I am breathing in long.
Breathing in long he knows I am
breathing in long.
Breathing in short breathing out long
Yeah that's how I'm breathing out.
long and then short And then it then it
moves to he
So that's that's what you could say like
um
Having breathing in short enduring Yeah.
he knows I am breathing in short. Yeah.
Having breathing out long enduring he
knows I am breathing out long. There's
this thing there. Because of that I am
breathing in like this or I am breathing
like that not because I am breathing
like this or that. I second it to it.
In other words I is basically just an
expression as in I know that because of
this breath this is the breath here.
There's something there and I know it's
there. And the body is there.
And the body is there.
Well that's why Anapanasati
the the sutta doesn't say the results in
jhanas and ecstatic experiences it
results in fulfillment of the four
foundations of mindfulness. Why?
The four foundations of recollection is
the four basis of recollection is
recollection of the body recollection of
the presently enduring feeling on
account of the body
recollection of the of the mind of the
moods recollection of the of the images. But But
yeah so
it then after these those first four
it's it's more about what
one should do or what one train how one
should do or what one train how one
Yeah what one intends to do.
That's right so it's um
so he trains I will breathe in
as one who experiences the whole body.
So the emphasis is on experiencing the
whole body. That's the goal.
That's what you're aiming for.
while breathing Yeah while breathing cuz
now that your mind is established upon
knowing the breathing that's enduring
there breathing in like this breathing
in like that. Whichever way the
breathing in is occurring he knows that.
Yeah. While it's occurring he's not
doing doing of the breathing.
So now that he knows
that there is um
breathing in long
and while breathing in long or breathing
in short he knows now he becomes
familiar with the knowledge in other
words the context of uh present
knowledge of present enduring breathing
is there.
Then he makes the effort to discern
further things within that container now
of established recollection.
And so it's not that Because you can
just stay with breathing and not think
about anything specific but the the
reason why the Buddha instead gave the
sutta is to for those who are still not
arahants to become arahants. So you need
to push a bit but not push in terms of
start doing the breathing which is
undoable so to speak. It's in in
independent of you your body. But more
like while you are now established with
that right container free from lust free
from aversion free from distraction
while you're breathing in like this
bring these phenomena to your mind.
Bring these images of the
uh body as a whole calming down joy
All the other things they would fortify
further this passion removal of lust and
removal of ignorance.
Can I just say as well it's not so much
that the
the
experiencing the body is then something
So so if if the breathing is peripheral
if the knowledge of the breathing is
peripheral then it's not so much that
the experiencing the whole body is then
something that you're staring at as
well. discernment. Exactly that's within Cuz
discernment. Exactly that's within Cuz
that's what I said it the body is there.
Yeah. That is that is the body Yeah.
while you're breathing that is what the
body is for you.
same place Exactly the same place.
That's that's what the sutta says. You
refine more you're you're discerning
more of the background.
Discern more of relevant background for
the freedom from suffering.
That's what I mean like push but not
push by creating or doing something now
on top of this.
Same principle.
You can only discern recollect that
which is there
on its own.
You're not creating it through your
recollection of it.
As the word recollection means
re-gathering of what's there on its own.
of what's there on its own.
So even breathing in like this
experiencing the whole body is breathing
in like this and fully like discerning
further the context of the body there
which is a necessary basis for any type
of breathing in fully or unfully. It
doesn't matter how, the body needs to be
there. Same like again so you discern
the body that's there on its own
seen through the context of of
breathing. You discern the feeling
that's there on its own seen through the
context of of breathing.
And that's why it's said the the the
body there is one of it's the body.
Yeah. The body
The body
body among bodies whatever translation
is. Uh the feeling there stands for the
Uh the feeling there stands for the
feeling. The mind there stands for the
mind and the images stand the full
images.
But you can't do that. You know you
can't do like it's satipatthana
basically. That's what satipatthana is.
And you can't do satipatthanas.
Uh you can discern them. That's why he
knows to the extent necessary for the
final knowledge. He knows not he does.
So what about this he trains in calming?
The body there.
It's the same. He breathes in like this
calming body. He I shall calm the body
while breathing in long.
I will breathe in short while calming
the body.
Yeah passambayam.
So
what does that mean?
Uh
Means the the image of calmness.
Yeah. Calming calming the bodily
determinations. kayasankhara kara Mhm.
So we're calming the determination of
the body.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
Which is the body that's there. Exactly.
Yeah. The image the image of the body
that is there. Whatever it is because of
which you know there's a body there. All
of that. So you can put it like this.
While you're breathing in while you know
that you're breathing in long
while you know you're breathing in short
there is an image of the body implied in
it in that experience as a whole. There
is an implicit image of the body.
Discerning that image. The way it has
its the way it's
it's implied.
Not the way you imply it.
The way you find it being implied you
keep discerning it further.
And that's the definition of of
mindfulness of the body as well.
Body in the body. Image of the body
within the body.
But image of the body within the image
of the body. Same.
Same.
You go for the feelings.
So he recognizes the calmness so to
speak. He finds the calmness
of that. What are you talking about? The
passambayam. So but the the the the
So but the the the the
So he trains in discernment of the
calmness. Yeah but yeah sure sure. He discerns the
Yeah but yeah sure sure. He discerns the
calmness. Yeah cuz you can you can
discern the
the non-calmness. You can discern
non-calmness. And by focusing on that
Yeah. You you choose to attend basically the
You you choose to attend basically the
the the signs of calmness or you can
choose to attend the signs of of
disturbance. The signs of the signs of the signs of
The signs of the signs of the signs of
aversion. So you choose the opposite
signs. The signs that are of the calm
dispositions. So the signs of calmness
your body calm or you slow down your
breathing. Exactly. You discern the calmness. You
Exactly. You discern the calmness. You
discern the element of calmness within
that experience as a whole and that's
why it results in calmness.
Yeah cuz you can recognize if you
recognize the body. Yeah. You recognize
the calm. Yeah. See if if and you could
see like we we described it beforehand
as indifferent to you. What is one of
the characteristics of things being
indifferent? Being equanimous. Being equanimous.
Undisturbed.
Calm. So dwell on the sign of this
experience of breathing is indifferent
to me. Yeah.
And you are dwelling on the sign of
calmness. Or rather this body You are
calming. Yeah. The body the image of the
body implicit in the in the experience
of breathing in long the image of the
body implicit in the experience of
breathing breathing out short or
whichever way it is.
That image is unconcerned. You dwell on
that now further.
And then he accepts one who experiences
joy pleasure.
Yeah so the pleasure of calm you can Pleasure
so the pleasure of calm you can Pleasure
of being undisturbed. Yeah.
The pleasure of being free from weight
of the burden of responsibility cuz
you're not breathing. You're just
knowing what breathing is there.
So it already reveals basically the
nature of
being free from responsibility for
actions for doing. Doing intentions do
for doing. Doing intentions do
themselves. For the arahant. Mhm.
But you're striving towards it so you
won't understand how's that possible
without negating my responsibility in in
place inherent initial responsibility
for it.
Uh
you get to understand that as well.
And you can't
know that you're breathing in without
also you know there being a mind there for
you know there being a mind there for
you to Of course. Yeah. Well whenever
there is an image whenever there is a
feeling there's a mind there.
That you can you cannot know that you're
breathing in like this while you're
experiencing overall uh
overall uh
imperturbable feeling of neutral
pleasure and say but my mind and my mood is
and say but my mind and my mood is
elsewhere. Yeah. No that is what your
mood is. That that's why it becomes your
mood. That's why you become calm
undisturbed and agreeable.
And that's again
that's why the Buddha was teaching it to
sotapannas or higher but to become
arahants. Mhm.
Means it will result in full knowledge.
Yeah. In full understanding. Not in
magical revelations in full
understanding of that which they will
understand fully through recollecting
it. Yeah. Which they already know it
there. Yeah. As a principle to some
extent. Yeah. But just So mindfulness of
Yeah. But just So mindfulness of
breathing yeah will basically uh
keep recollecting of the right things.
It will it will basically maintain it
keep it enduring until the mind is
completely free from the asavas. So he's
telling them to train themselves in
breathing in
and breathing in with a composed mind
with a liberated mind. Yeah. All all the
all the characteristics of the mind free
from suffering. Characteristics that
they understood in the principle at
least. What liberation is.
What liberation is.
That's why they can recollect it.
And then these notions of composure and
and and liberation as basically being
these
now you they're moving on to train
uh training oneself breathing in as one
who sees impermanence. Yeah. So these
fundamental kind of
images that
will only anicca being again
if if the image of the body that's
being implicitly now
uh
the you are subjected to it
through your
through your um
recollecting the context of your
breathing. You're recollecting the context of the
You're recollecting the context of the
breathing
and there is an emerging image of the
body implied there.
But can you have breathing without a
body? Can you breathe in out
Can you breathe in out
breathe in or out long or short
uh quick or slow without the body? So
the body is there and you get to discern
the image of the body in the basically
breathing of the body.
The characteristics of that image now
that's being discerned within the
context of this peripheral
recollectiveness of me breathing in
breathing out breathing in like this
breathing out like that.
Breathing in in short breathing out
short occurring breathing out long
occurring.
What are the characteristics of that
body? And then I was subjected to it.
And then I was subjected to it.
Subjected to it indifferent to me.
Doesn't care about unownable.
Yeah. Which is what anicca is. Yeah.
Ah let me now maybe emphasize with my
discernment the aspect of anicca of this
which is already there enduring on its
own through the recollecting that which
was there on its own.
So it results in anicca. It will result
in anicca even if you don't think about
anicca. And when it won't result in anicca is
And when it won't result in anicca is
when you do it.
But it's try When you are doing it when
you are the one in control when you are
the one originating it means you are
acting with the assumption of owning it.
That's why you're doing it. And how can
you then see the unownability of it?
You can't.
So the only way to see anicca of the
mindfulness of breathing is to see
breath there on its own and know it on
its own for what it is.
Thus breathing in long he knows I'm
breathing in long.
Not I choose to breathe in long and
that's why I know I'm breathing in long.
So whatever breath is there you know
that that's what you're breathing.
Not because you want to breathe in but
because that's what you're subjected to.
Only then will you be possible to train
yourself in regards And then you get to
discern all these other things on the
level of the images on the level of of
of dhammas on the level of the mind and
moods as things enduring that you're
also subjected to in the same manner you
were subjected to this doing of this
breathing. Which is kind of another reason why
Which is kind of another reason why
breathing is a good thing to do is is
something everybody would regard as the most
everybody would regard as the most
personal thing. Well, yeah, I was going
to ask why why is it Why is the
breathing a good object? Uh
that's why. Because it's the most
personal type of action, seemingly. But
you realize that the most personal type
of action, the most internal, the most
inseparable, the most unoptional type of
action you are subjected to. Yeah.
And it's also that's why it's neutral.
You don't need to have desire or
aversion, you will be breathing.
So it precedes
all the other types of actions that your
mind usually depends on. And isn't it
also like like your bodily posture is
something that you you're always doing.
It's not like uh
No, but the reason why it's why it's a
it's a good thing to like develop the
context in regard to as in something of
it
Yeah, yeah.
is because it's neutral, yet it contains
the nature of the action. It is an
action, or at least that's the view.
So while like can you be can you breathe
in long? If the body is not breathing in
long. Huh?
Huh?
So even when you say I am breathing in
long, the only reason you can
assume the possession of it is cuz the
body is doing it.
Because you notice that there's
something there which is the body
breathing in.
So in the same sense as we described in
other talks, I don't really know the
order I'm uploading them, but people
will come across it. We said like the
body as a representative of the only
matter that you are exposed to. That's
the to your body is your universe. If
you try to like repossess the matter,
the matter rupa, it's always step below
your feet.
The distance always remains the same.
You cannot possibly enter the the world
behind these appearances cuz that's
another assumption based on these
appearances. You're fully enclosed
within this. Entering your knowledge.
The breath is the same.
Doesn't matter how slow how controllably
you're doing your breath, you are within
it. Yeah.
It's not within you.
the breathing yeah, you are within the
breathing. There's always
Because you're within the body.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's why the Buddha
taught it instead of in another
mindfulness of death.
I I I got that's like it's the same
wording by the way. It's the same
wording for the bodily postures. It's
exactly the same. So sitting down Yeah,
you're within
understands I'm sitting down. Breathing in, he
I'm sitting down. Breathing in, he
understands I'm breathing.
Yeah, sure. It's the foundation Yeah.
It's the it's the foundations of
recollectiveness. But then another suta the when we done
But then another suta the when we done
the mindfulness
the breathing towards death, it was when
monks were practicing marana marana
sati. And then
And then
asuba. Yeah, they got a bit got a bit
edgy. Yeah. Asuba and so on. So so they
were committing suicide and so on. So
that the Buddha instead of that Yeah.
But for the same result, practice the
breathing. Practice the breathing. You
won't jump off cliffs then. Yeah, but it
still is going to develop the same
mindfulness of the same death being the
same container you cannot step outside
of. Yeah.
Yeah.
Usually you don't notice your breath.
You might discern that your body is your
container, your senses are your
container, the world is a container, my
possessions are my container and so on,
depending how undeveloped your mind is.
But fundamentally, the most immediate
container is the image of the body of
breathing in breathing out. And that's
much closer to everything else you do
while you are breathing.
So there is really no closer to that.
Well, mindfulness of death is closer to
that. Like after removal of anything anything
Like after removal of anything anything
any necessary basis for that experience
the whole that's why it can result
quickly in full uprooting of this
passion or it can tip you over a bit
too quickly.
So not as close as mindfulness of death,
but there is nothing closer
except that.
To the point of view developing in terms
of
where you're enclosed within. Can you
imagine being outside?
Can you imagine doing anything without
breathing body? Like even if like there
is
you're holding your breathing Yeah. It's
only done on account of the breathing
body, now delaying the breathing of the
now delaying the breathing of the
breathing body.
Like how can you be holding it if it's
not there?
And basically the intention to breathe
is still there. You can't Of course. You
can't get a step outside of that.
The possibility of breath is still
there. The action of breathing is still there.
Cuz you know,
what about the heart? The beating of
heart. I breathe I I beat in Yeah. quick, I
I breathe I I beat in Yeah. quick, I
beat in
No, see you can contemplate that, but
that would be more on the level of
marana sati. Yeah.
And that's why you could see how it
could just
fill somebody with anxiety. If you
recognize it literally, if you do see a
connection how entire your entire life
You just said that beat. How your entire
life of joys and miseries of of of
everything things that are important,
your value, possessions, everything
literally depends on this random beat
that you have you can't even conceive
controlling. You can conceive
controlling breath, which is why it's a
good converging point to undo that
conceiving. This will just cut through your own
This will just cut through your own
conceivings and if the mind is strong
enough, that cutting through would
result in like yeah, full dispassion and
arahantship. If the mind is not strong
enough, well, that cutting through might
cut you.
As it did to a certain number of monks
when they were jumping off the cliffs
and whatnot. They couldn't handle it. But breathing
But breathing
like there is an assumption of my
involvement with it.
So it's not that I'm just so randomly
subjected to in utter utter lack of
control. But that
But that
that's that any sense of control you
have over your breathing is undercut by
is within the breathing that you are
subjected to so that you realize my
sense of control
is basically not
cannot become primordial. Cannot take
the possession of its necessary basis
for my control.
something as basic as breathing.
But it's a neutral
It's a neutral action. Yeah, so it will
not result necessarily
destroying this disgusting. It's just
breathing. And then oh, I'm fully
enclosed within this just breathing. I
cannot step outside of this breathing.
So If you stop maintaining the
assumption of ownership stepping outside
as we discussed it before, the
assumption of external in regard to this
breathing what is then to be said about all the
what is then to be said about all the
other even more proliferate assumptions?
They would be abandoned.
So you think your body is here, that's
why you're breathing.
Your notion of body is here because
you're breathing is there.
So when you choose to act on account of
your body, that's even further down the
line.
You are subjected to breathing. That's
why you know the body.
That's why I know the body.
That's why you can relate to the body.
That's why you can possess the body.
That's why you can chase the sense
objects to the body for the body and so
on. Or you could say you're sitting down.
Or you could say you're sitting down.
That's why you know the body.
Could you not say that as well? Yes, but
now you're talking about a different I
know, but just like it's not like yeah,
it's not the only way you can know know
the body. No, we're talking about
mindfulness of breathing.
You can know the body through the
postures that the body has been
subjected to.
You can know the body through
contemplating death of the body.
That's why these things are
contemplations.
That's why sati recollectiveness results
in in full understanding, in wisdom, in
discernment, whatever you want to call
it. See directly yeah, if you keep
See directly yeah, if you keep
recollecting it, you become more
familiar with it. More familiar with it,
the more signs and tokens and features
of it become discerned.
The more it gets established.
But with when you're when you're doing a
technique breathing technique which there are many
breathing technique which there are many
out there to calm your body to
give you energy or whatever. You have
fears, so you
breathe in, you don't breathe you
breathe in deep.
Breathe in shallow, whatever, to manage
a certain experience you're having that
you don't want to be. Fear,
anger, excitement, you want to be calm.
So those things are they work,
but that is not
that is not
you don't have the knowledge
of what a nature is.
Yeah. So if you don't have the So they don't
So if you don't have the So they don't
work.
So you You have to define what working
is. You can't say oh, it helps me, thus
it works. It's a management form.
Working means it frees you from
suffering, frees you from need of
management. Basically, it if if things
are working, they will make you unable
to be affected by issues in the first
place. Not just they will perfectly manage the
Not just they will perfectly manage the
issues.
So if things are not working on that
level, then things are not working.
So if your working is on the level of
management, you you shouldn't call it
the same working as the level of
uprooting that which I'm managing now.
Just to say
Because if you're not affected in the
first place, there is nothing for you to
manage. But it's
But it's
often that's kept intentionally that
that that blur between well, it it maybe
doesn't work for us to be a sotapanna,
but it still works. Well, how do you
know unless you're a sotapanna? So then
it doesn't work.
But yes, so the management when it's
used as management, it can help
manage the pain, but that's again or
manage the difficult, manage the issues.
But all of those things are secondary to
the fact that the issues are first.
That's the thing. The word manage all of
it implies something wrong.
Yeah, exactly. To manage, you require a
problem in order to manage it. But But
the Dhamma doesn't manage the problems,
the Dhamma uproots them. So mindfulness
of breathing, the Buddha said, if you
have the right view, it will result in
arahantship if you cultivate and make
much of it.
Means it it's about uprooting, not about
perfect management. It's about making
you unable to be affected by that which
you used to have to manage.
Freedom from management.
Yeah, freedom from burden.
That's that's a form of burden, having
to do something on account of what you
felt, on account of what touched you,
what contacted you.
You have to do it. You can't help but
doing it.
You're burdened.
Pressure. You're free from all of that.
So, that's what I mean, if you're doing
it as a technique,
it cannot result in the right context
because your current context of doing it
as a technique is the context of
management. Why? Why why do you want to do a
Why? Why why do you want to do a
meditation breathing?
Because you're bothered by something or
because you want something that you
don't have, which is what bothers you.
So, that's your context. Are you fully
understanding and discerning that
context
through you watching your nostrils?
Not at all. You're just hoping that
watching your nostrils will result in
fulfilling your wishes.
Hence, you meditate with sensuality, as
the Buddha said.
Cuz by the way, you can't like not being
aware of the context doesn't mean the
context is not there.
Just means you're unaware of it. Means
you're ignoring it.
Like we said. Avijja, the ignorance, the
utmost thing
you can do. It's indifferent to your
nature. It's indifferent to you, yeah.
So, what is the context of you needing a
meditation method, a direct set of
precise instruction what to do, what to
observe? What is the context of that
experience? Desire.
Desire.
Desire? Rooted in what? In how you feel?
So, are you understanding these things?
Well, no, you can't. It's mutually
exclusive. You'll either start looking
at the context
and by doing so become familiar with it,
allow it to endure, recollect it.
Recollect your desire to be free from
suffering not when you go and sit to
watch your nostrils, but when you want
to go out with your friends and drink or
break precepts or or whatever else. Or
as a monk, you want to distract yourself
with work or or
or group or other monks,
socializing or whatever else. Recollect
that context and you won't do these
things. That's what mindfulness is, not like
That's what mindfulness is, not like
sitting and
breathing in and out.
And that's why mindfulness of breathing
results in mindfulness being developed
on the or four
four reference points.
Satipatthana. Nothing else. He said, this anapanasati
Nothing else. He said, this anapanasati
fully developed only results in
developing of the four foundations of
mindfulness, which results in the
four right strivings, which then results
in development of the seven
enlightenment factors, which basically
makes you free from all passion and
become an arahant.
So, if you still have a need to like
focus on the tip of your nose when
you're breathing,
look at the context why.
That's where your mindfulness is.
It's not you looking at the breath. It's
you having a certain context making you
do that.
That's why you can't just do pure
mindfulness, either.
The context is effortless.
Yeah, discerning the context, that's
always effortless cuz that's always
there on its own.
What you do on account of the context,
that's not effortless.
That's something you can be burdened by
or freed from.
I must do this when like when it's this
or I I don't have to do anything.
And you know, the Buddha said many times
you can't have you can't overdo
mindfulness. But equanimity is focusing practice. You
But equanimity is focusing practice. You
can never do that.
Can you really not overdo that?
Yeah. Yeah, you can very much overdo it, which
Yeah, you can very much overdo it, which
means it's completely not that.
And again, why are you why are you
focusing?
Why are you focusing on the touching
points And if you got it right
And if you got it right
body on the chair? Why are you focusing
on the nostrils? Why?
Why would I be doing that?
Finding out why is discerning the
context that's making you do it.
Discerning the mindfulness, it's it's
recollecting that because of which you
are acting in this manner.
Coming aware of your responsibility,
your action and everything else.
Not relying on a magical kind of results
that will come out of this
like mindless performance of these
methods and techniques.
Cuz you would you perform a method
method method to it and it builds method
you're doing it 1 2 2 hours 3 hours 4
hours for but then something comes up in
your life
you're you're
the experience the joy that you get
Yeah, it's it's it's it's That's what I
mean like you can't do the method
without the context that makes you do
it. And that context is where your view
is. And in this case in that case, it
would be the view of expecting results
as at the end of this performance of
this set of motions.
building up the mindfulness building up
And that would be a magic combination.
If you if you understand the context
you can't lose it.
Well, not just that. It's basically the
fact that you you're implying that you
can build up this focusing practice that
would result in this energy release
means your view is of a nature that that
puts the value of things that happen to
you as a result of this which you do,
which means your practice then
results of your practice you as thinking
come or not. You don't know for sure.
You don't know how much means there is
no direct knowledge between this is
what's done and this is the result of
this passion between it. You don't see
that. Which means there is no knowledge
between uh suffering and what do I do to be free
uh suffering and what do I do to be free
from it.
It's just I'm subject to suffering and
I'm doing these things to what extent,
how, when, I don't know. I just have
faith that doing this will free me from
this. Yet, the beginning of the right doing of
Yet, the beginning of the right doing of
the sotapanna is knowing exactly what
you're supposed to do, how, how much and
what it would result in.
In other words, he knows the way out of
suffering. He's not just hoping for it
through like performing sets of duties
and virtues and observances
and techniques and methods.
That's the difference. So, that is the
context of if you if you're practicing
your meditation with these expectations,
that is your context. You expect it to
happen to you, which means you you don't
know how you are supposed to develop it.
Cuz that that whole knowledge doesn't
have to be
to have that knowledge again
you can have to build up time through
focusing meditation.
meditation.
You know, you do 1 hour of meditation, 2
hours meditation. You build up that
knowledge again that you had when you
did that 2-week retreat with 10 hours a
day. But that if you have the knowledge, it's
But that if you have the knowledge, it's
always there. You can't not lose it. You
can't uh
you don't have to figure it out all
again. Yeah, that's that's the definition of
Yeah, that's that's the definition of
the knowledge, yeah. You don't if you
have And you wouldn't have you wouldn't have
And you wouldn't have you wouldn't have
developed that knowledge by by by doing
your your technique for 3 hours. Cuz as
I said again, the point of it is taking
you away from the context, putting the
emphasis of it will happen to me,
whatever I'm hoping for. No, it's like I
will develop it. If you think you you
have to build up your understanding
again means you don't understand
anything. If you have to figure it out
means you again
cuz you figured out before. Yeah.
Well, if you have to figure it out, genuinely
if you have to figure it out, genuinely
figure it out, that's fine. That's just
how you're basically making effort to
contemplate and overcome the doubt.
So, as long as we're not confusing the
actual trying to understand for watching
your nostrils. That's not even remotely
close to that.
Uh but yeah, somebody who doesn't have
fully confirmed confidence in his own
knowledge, knowing right is right, wrong
is wrong, will have to keep going back
and doing it and doing it and doing it.
And when I say doing it, I mean trying
to reclarify it.
To understand this, how do I regard
this? Passion has arisen, why is that?
Why do I Why did I attend?
Yeah, by all means, do all that as much
as you want. Yeah, it can result in
restlessness, but it certainly do result
in developing discernment.
But once you understood that mindfulness
is effortless
Yeah, yeah. Well, that's a completely
one thing, but what I'm talking about is
when people would like not even make the
effort to understand, but expect
understanding to come out of a
mechanical observation of my nostrils.
Literally, belief is on that level.
So, there's absolutely absolutely no,
not even a trace of conflating that with
trying to understand and actually
discerning that which you're becoming
familiar with.
Cuz you're not becoming familiar with
anything except with the greatness of
the expectation that understanding will
happen to me as a result of this.
But understanding doesn't happen to it.
You develop it. That's what the Buddha
said, it cannot be taken away once it's
developed cuz it wasn't given
to you externally by any means. And once
it's developed, all you're doing is
discerning something that's there on its
own that Which is why it can be
developed, yeah.
And and why also it can't be taken away
because it's already there. Yeah, of
course. It's a necessary basis for
things that used to be taken away. Even
they were within that level.
You're not creating a context to your
practice. Exactly. Exactly, yeah. You're undoing
Exactly. Exactly, yeah. You're undoing
the wrong context.
Which is as I said, there always has to
be some context. So, it's either wrong
context or it's closer to the right
context. So, by becoming aware of the context
So, by becoming aware of the context
even as a puthujjana, context of
responsibility, context of the lack of
knowledge, context of being subjected to
suffering all the time even when I don't
necessarily suffer, I'm still of the
nature to suffer, I'm prey to suffering.
Let that context dwell in your mind and
see how unwholesome or careless you get
in the world. You won't cuz you will be
on edge always cuz you're always
responsible.
And then as the Buddha said, the noble
search would be a natural result of it.
I need to do like This is the utmost.
This is the only thing worth doing.
Doing something about this.
What I'm subject to.
And then you get to learn more. As in
then you're open to the like with the
without looking for faults, you're open
to the right instruction and you will be
able to hear it
when you come across it.
Cuz you you you are you have clarified
even as a puthujjana the basis on to to
which the right instruction applies.
If you don't have that basis, you can
have the Buddha like face to face
telling you you wouldn't see it, you
wouldn't know it, and you wouldn't
understand the value of what he said.
As many cases in the suttas happened.
But if you have clarified the value of
that context of what you're subjected to
as a puthujjana,
even a second-hand account of the
Buddha's teaching would be enough for
you.
Because you've done the work of
uncluttering the mess of ignoring.
And then further you want to
develop full understanding of the
context is just more of the same.
More of uncluttering, more of protecting
what you clarified, what you
recollected, letting it endure until you become
letting it endure until you become
sufficiently familiar to the extent
necessary for the final knowledge.
So, how you feeling right now?
It's basically recollect what's present
enduring mood.
Now, can you recollect how long has that
mood been enduring even before you
recollected it? You can cuz recollection
within recollection
is again within the same recollection.
And if that thing were not enduring on
its own,
you wouldn't be able to remember it.
How long it was there before. So, recollect
So, recollect
that you're still subject to suffering.
And now when you sit, stand, walk, talk,
eat, drink,
sleep, whatever else, keep that context
in your mind.
I am subject to suffering while I'm
doing these things.
That's what I mean like the sati is
opposite of focusing.
You can't focus
on the context
for your intention to focus.
Trying to focus on the base of your
focusing is like literally trying to see
your eye with its own eye.
And you can see the harder than you're
trying to focus,
the less you see.
Yeah, and you might confuse that for some
and you might confuse that for some
mystical experience. Yeah, goes hand in
hand with a conflated context and so on.
with a conflated context and so on.
But I we we spoke about it before. You
mentioned it as well the
like when you come first and you know,
you like
living the forest, the jungle, snakes
and so on.
Until you're used to it, you're just
like like like looking at everything cuz
you still don't have the context.
You don't have the con- You have the
context of the danger, but that needs to
be clarified now. It's it's it's not
specific, so you don't really know what
to look for, what is dangerous, what
isn't. So, okay, you know snakes are dangerous,
So, okay, you know snakes are dangerous,
but like even that, you think all the
snakes are dangerous.
And there are actually very few that
are. And they're rarely seen, but initially
And they're rarely seen, but initially
any snake means the same danger. So, you
end up going and like wary of everything
cuz that's your context. But then the
more you dwell in that context, and by
the way, you don't need the snakes to
focus on them for the context of the
danger of the snakes. Quite the
opposite. The danger is when you don't
see it. When you see it, it's 10 m away,
it's no danger.
It's by not seeing it, by not being able
to focus on it, that's where the context
is discerned.
And once you become familiar with it, it
becomes the normal. So, you're not
necessarily even feeling the the same
weight or the same like mood in regard
to that context cuz it became the norm.
You've been doing it, you got used to
it. But it doesn't mean it's not there.
Cuz as as we were joking before like you
you step and like a a blade of grass
sort of
touches your ankle with an unusual angle
and immediately your mind is on full.
Like you don't think,
"I was touched. I must focus on my foot
now. I must retract my foot." As soon as
it touches you, your foot is away from
it. And then you look and find out what it
And then you look and find out what it
was cuz the context of the danger is
still there and remains enduring there
all this time. The significance of the
touch is already within seen against the
backdrop of the right context.
Context that is important to you, that
is significant to you such as protect my
life. So,
So,
if you do the mindful If you do
recollecting this correctly, even your
focusing will be effortless.
I focus on what is that.
It's effortless. You won't require
effort. It will come naturally as a
result of the right rightly established
context. Yeah, it it trickles trickles down. It
Yeah, it it trickles trickles down. It
exactly exactly. This is what we're
doing, guys. And then everyone starts
doing their job. You don't have to worry
about it.
And you can't reverse engineer it by
hoping to focus focus focus somehow the
context will be
Yeah, will kind of miraculously merge.
That would be true if there is no
if there is no context at certain times.
So, if you could be acting without
context, then you could discern the
context within your particular acts.
But there is always a context. So, you
acting without a specific context is
your context
while you're acting in that manner.
That's why the only way to start
discerning the context is to start
looking at the context even if it's
all the aimless signal, ignoring things,
not wanting to think. All these things
are part of your context.
So, then discerning the right context is
not figuring it out
like creating it rightly, it's just
undoing everything that obscures it
literally. So, it's the opposite way of
the way they would you're focusing and
your method would take you.
It's the way of uncluttering the net the
context of the clutter that made me do
the focusing.
Uncovering, yeah.
Uncovering, yeah. But not through that
which resulted at
not through that which is the result of
the context of this is covered, I need
to uncover it.
That's what I mean like ask yourself
why. Whatever practice you're doing, ask
yourself why. That's where the context
is. And then you can
certainly step closer to see whether
what you're doing is actually
resulting out of the context
or trying to manage it or is it actually
really aiming to approve the context.
And there's no method that can teach you
how to stop ignoring the context.
Only stop ignoring it.
Well, the closer to the method that can
teach you how to stop ignoring it is the
precepts. They will not necessarily teach you how
They will not necessarily teach you how
to stop ignoring the context, but will
start you emulating
the non-wrong context.
Behavior of the non-wrong context.
That's why
you know, sense restraint, celibacy and
so on are necessary.